Finding Aid for Bryant Walker papers, 1873-1931
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Bryant Walker papers 1873-1931
Walker, Bryant, 1856-1936.
10 linear feet
86285 Aa 2
Detroit, Michigan attorney, shell collector and student of conchology. Correspondence, notebooks, and lists relating primarily to his interest in mollusca and shell collecting; also copies of family letters, 1830-1841, written from Buffalo, New York, Grand Rapids and Detroit, Michigan; a University of Michigan student notebook from a course in physics, 1874.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Calvin Goodrich (donor no. 125 ) and came to the library in 1937.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Bryant Walker was born July 3, 1856 in Detroit, Michigan. He graduated from the University of Michigan (A.B. 1876) then began the study of law in the office of Walker & Kent. He was admitted to the Michigan bar in 1878. The following year he received his LL.B degree from the University of Michigan. He then became a partner with his father in the firm of Walker & Walker.
Beyond the law, Walker's great interest was conchology. He became an authority on mollusca and was a noted collector of conchological specimens. He wrote numerous articles on conchology for magazine and the proceedings of various societies. His professional memberships included the Malacological Society of London, the Conchological Society of Britain and Ireland, the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia, and the Michigan Academy of Science. He died May 26, 1936.
The Bryant Walker collection consists largely of correspondence from throughout the world with conchologists. There are, in addition, his manuscripts of his writings, various lists, charts, and inventories, and miscellaneous family materials and a University of Michigan student notebook of a class on physics.
Subjects:
Buffalo (N.Y.); Detroit (Mich.); Grand Rapids (Mich.); Lawyers--Michigan--Detroit.; New York (State); Shells.; University of Michigan--Student notebooks.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Walker, Bryant, 1856-1936.; Shells.
Genre Terms:
Drawings.; Photographs.; Prints.
- Correspondence
  - 1873-1902 (Box 1)
  - 1903-1909 (Box 2)
  - 1910-April 1914 (Box 3)
  - May 1914-February 1919 (Box 4)
  - March 1919-January 1924 (Box 5)
  - February 1924-December 1927 (Box 6)
  - January 1928-March 1931 (Box 7)
  - 1925-1928 letters to John N. Lowe (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, miscellaneous and undated, 5 folders (Box 7)
- Mollusca and shell collecting
  - List of shells, 6 folders (Box 7)
  - Catalog of shell prices (Sowerby family collection) (Box 7)
  - Paraguay and Uruguay miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - Manuscripts
    - "Hunting Mollusca in Utah and Idaho in 1916" (Box 7)
    - "Ancylidae of South Africa" (Box 7)
    - "The New Conchology" (Box 7)
    - "The Molluscan Hosts of Chlonorchis Sinensis Cobb. in Japan, China and Southeastern Asia Asiatic Mollusks" (Box 7)
    - "Origin and Distribution of North American Mollusks" (Box 7)
    - "The Shell Bearing Mollusks of Michigan" (Box 7)
    - "Census of Michigan Mollusks" (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts of published papers, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Sketches and prints of snails, 6 folders (Box 8)
  - Graphs and maps (Box 8)
  - Maps charting distribution of Alabama land snails (Box 8)
  - Letterpress book 1877-1886 (Box 8)
  - Notebooks contain lists of shells in Walker collection; also miscellaneous notes (Box 9)
- Other conchologists
  (includes materials collected by Walker or received with Walker papers)
  - Correspondence of Truman Aldrich (of Alabama) (Box 10)
  - Correspondence and other papers of Mrs. George Andrews (of Tenn.), 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Correspondence and notebooks of A.E. Daniels (Box 10)
  - Synopsis of the collection of mollusca of the late J. H. Ponsonby (Box 10)
  - Correspondence and other papers of Berlin Hart Wright, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Catalogues of E. Pleas (Box 10)
  - Notebooks of Manly Miles (Box 10)
  - Letter and drawings of Horace Baker (Box 10)
- Other materials
  - University of Michigan student notebook (Physics) 1874 (Box 10)
  - Speech: "The Seigniory of Sault Ste. Marie" (not Bryant Walker's) (Box 10)
  - Student papers 1875-1878
    - More's Utopia (Box 10)
    - English 17th Century Political History (Box 10)
    - Comparison of English-and United States Judiciary (Box 10)
    - Michigan shells (Box 10)
  - Typescript of Walker family letters 1830-1841 written from Buffalo, New York, Grand Rapids and Detroit (Box 10)
  - Photographs: portraits and informal photographs (Box 10)